Distributed Git
Now that you have a remote Git repository set up as a focal point for all the developers to share
their code, and you’re familiar with basic Git commands in a local workflow, you’ll look at how to
utilize some of the distributed workflows that Git affords you.
In this chapter, you’ll see how to work with Git in a distributed environment as a contributor and
an integrator. That is, you’ll learn how to contribute code successfully to a project and make it as
easy on you and the project maintainer as possible, and also how to maintain a project successfully
with a number of developers contributing.
Distributed Workflows
Unlike Centralized Version Control Systems (CVCSs), the distributed nature of Git allows you to be
far more flexible in how developers collaborate on projects. In centralized systems, every
developer is a node working more or less equally on a central hub. In Git, however, every
developer is potentially both a node and a hub — that is, every developer can both contribute code
to other repositories and maintain a public repository on which others can base their work and
which they can contribute to. This opens a vast range of workflow possibilities for your project
and/or your team, so we’ll cover a few common paradigms that take advantage of this flexibility.
We’ll go over the strengths and possible weaknesses of each design; you can choose a single one to
use, or you can mix and match features from each.
Centralized Workflow
In centralized systems, there is generally a single collaboration model — the centralized workflow.
One central hub, or repository, can accept code, and everyone synchronizes their work to it. A
number of developers are nodes — consumers of that hub — and synchronize to that one place.
Figure 54. Centralized workflow.
This means that if two developers clone from the hub and both make changes, the first developer to
push their changes back up can do so with no problems. The second developer must merge in the
first one’s work before pushing changes up, so as not to overwrite the first developer’s changes.
117
This concept is as true in Git as it is in Subversion (or any CVCS), and this model works perfectly
well in Git.
If you are already comfortable with a centralized workflow in your company or team, you can
easily continue using that workflow with Git. Simply set up a single repository, and give everyone
on your team push access; Git won’t let users overwrite each other. Say John and Jessica both start
working at the same time. John finishes his change and pushes it to the server. Then Jessica tries to
push her changes, but the server rejects them. She is told that she’s trying to push non-fast-forward
changes and that she won’t be able to do so until she fetches and merges. This workflow is
attractive to a lot of people because it’s a paradigm that many are familiar and comfortable with.
This is also not limited to small teams. With Git’s branching model, it’s possible for hundreds of
developers to successfully work on a single project through dozens of branches simultaneously.
Integration-Manager Workflow
Because Git allows you to have multiple remote repositories, it’s possible to have a workflow where
each developer has write access to their own public repository and read access to everyone else’s.
This scenario often includes a canonical repository that represents the “official” project. To
contribute to that project, you create your own public clone of the project and push your changes to
it. Then, you can send a request to the maintainer of the main project to pull in your changes. The
maintainer can then add your repository as a remote, test your changes locally, merge them into
their branch, and push back to their repository. The process works as follows (see Integration-
manager workflow.):
1. The project maintainer pushes to their public repository.
2. A contributor clones that repository and makes changes.
3. The contributor pushes to their own public copy.
4. The contributor sends the maintainer an email asking them to pull changes.
5. The maintainer adds the contributor’s repository as a remote and merges locally.
6. The maintainer pushes merged changes to the main repository.
Figure 55. Integration-manager workflow.
This is a very common workflow with hub-based tools like GitHub or GitLab, where it’s easy to fork
a project and push your changes into your fork for everyone to see. One of the main advantages of
118
this approach is that you can continue to work, and the maintainer of the main repository can pull
in your changes at any time. Contributors don’t have to wait for the project to incorporate their
changes — each party can work at their own pace.
Dictator and Lieutenants Workflow
This is a variant of a multiple-repository workflow. It’s generally used by huge projects with
hundreds of collaborators; one famous example is the Linux kernel. Various integration managers
are in charge of certain parts of the repository; they’re called lieutenants. All the lieutenants have
one integration manager known as the benevolent dictator. The benevolent dictator pushes from
his directory to a reference repository from which all the collaborators need to pull. The process
works like this (see Benevolent dictator workflow.):
1. Regular developers work on their topic branch and rebase their work on top of master. The
master branch is that of the reference directory to which the dictator pushes.
2. Lieutenants merge the developers' topic branches into their master branch.
3. The dictator merges the lieutenants' master branches into the dictator’s master branch.
4. Finally, the dictator pushes that master branch to the reference repository so the other
developers can rebase on it.
Figure 56. Benevolent dictator workflow.
This kind of workflow isn’t common, but can be useful in very big projects, or in highly hierarchical
environments. It allows the project leader (the dictator) to delegate much of the work and collect
large subsets of code at multiple points before integrating them.
Workflows Summary
These are some commonly used workflows that are possible with a distributed system like Git, but
you can see that many variations are possible to suit your particular real-world workflow. Now that
you can (hopefully) determine which workflow combination may work for you, we’ll cover some
119
more specific examples of how to accomplish the main roles that make up the different flows. In
the next section, you’ll learn about a few common patterns for contributing to a project.